A Guide to the Eleanor H. Porter Collection
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #11109
Eleanor H. Porter Collection 1903-1936
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
11109
ca. 617 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Purchase 1993 October 20
Scope and Content
The collection contains manuscript and typescript drafts, frequently with pencilled corrections, and/or printed versions of over 30 short stories and the serialized novel Money, Love and Kate as well as galley sheets for Mary Marie.
Topics in her correspondence include bookings for the play Dawn; royalties; Swedish translation of Oh, Money! Money! the dramatization of Just David; a controversy over property rights to the name Pollyanna; her books A Minstrel of the Hills, Money, Love and Kate, The Nickel, and The Story of Marco Polo; copyright to her short stories; and motion picture rights to Sister Sue.
There is also correspondence of John Lyman Porter as executor of her estate.
In addition the collection contains legal papers including book contracts and a copy of her will; photographs of Porter and of Fred C. Hodgman; photograph albums of vacation and nature scenes and printed miscellaney.
Item Listing
- Manuscripts
  - "According to Rule" by Eleanor H. Porter, 10 p., in The Housewife, with pencilled corrections and changes, 1907; TMsS (Box Box 1)
  - "According to Rule" by Eleanor H. Porter, in The Housewife, pages 6-7, 1907 Nov; Printed (Box Box 1)
  - "An Accusative Suit Case" by Eleanor H. Porter, in 10 Story Book, pages 44-47, 1908 Jan; Printed (Box Box 1)
  - "As Tom Saw It" by Eleanor H. Porter, 9 p., in The Christian Herald, with pencilled corrections and changes, 1904; TMsS (Box Box 1)
  - "As Tom Saw It" by Eleanor H. Porter, in The Christian Herald, pages 125-126, 1904 Feb; Printed (Box Box 1)
  - "The Atonement of Hustler Joe" by Eleanor H. Porter, in Tom Watson's Magazine, pages 145-179, 1905 Apr; Printed (Box Box 1)
  - "Because of Tiglath-Pileser" by Eleanor H. Porter, 9 p., with pencilled corrections and changes, TMsS (Box Box 1)
  - "Beyond the Stars" by Eleanor H. Porter, 11 p., in Smith's Magazine, with pencilled corrections and changes, 1909; TMsS (Box Box 1)
  - "Beyond the Stars" by Eleanor H. Porter, in Smith's Magazine, pages 833-838, 1909 Aug; Printed (Box Box 1)
  - "Bones of Contention" by Eleanor H. Porter, 7 p., in The Pittsburgh Bulletin, with pencilled corrections and changes, 1904; TMsS (Box Box 1)
  - "Bones of Contention" by Eleanor H. Porter, in The Pittsburgh Bulletin, page 6, 1904 Jan; Printed (Box Box 1)
  - "By Aid of Helen Henrietta" by Eleanor H. Porter, in The Christian Herald, pages 752-753, 759-760, 1913 Aug; Printed (Box Box 1)
  - "The Cat That Played Cupid" by Eleanor H. Porter, 18 p., in New England Magazine, with pencilled corrections and changes, 1905; TMsS (Box Box 1)
  - "The Cat That Played Cupid" by Eleanor H. Porter, in New England Magazine, pages 461-467, 1905 Jun; Printed (Box Box 1)
  - "The Cheering Up of Miss Dearing" by Eleanor H. Porter, in The Congregationalist and Christian World, pages 727-728, 1913 Nov; Printed (Box Box 1)
  - "The Difference" by Eleanor H. Porter, in Lippincott's Monthly Magazine, page 32, in the back of the magazine with the advertisements, 1903 May; Printed (Box Box 1)
  - "The Fall of a Kitchen Barometer" by Eleanor H. Porter, n.d.; Printed (Box Box 1)
  - "The Flagging of 688" by Eleanor H. Porter, in Young's Magazine, pages 352-357, 1912 Jun; Printed (Box Box 1)
  - "For Mikey" by Eleanor H. Porter, pages 11-19, n.d.; AMs (Box Box 1)
  - "For Mikey" by Eleanor H. Porter, n.d.; 3 Printed (Box Box 1)
  - "For Miss Rachel -- A Thanksgiving" by Eleanor H. Porter, in The Housewife, pages 3-4, 1909 Nov; Printed (Box Box 1)
  - "How Patsey Went to Mont-Lawn" by Eleanor H. Porter, in The Christian Herald, pages 795-796, 1916 Jul 5; Printed (Box Box 1)
  - "Illustrated Proverbs" by Eleanor H. Porter, n.d.; Printed (Box Box 1)
  - "In the Face of Tradition" by Eleanor H. Porter, in Smith's Magazine, pages 78-84, 1911 Apr; Printed (Box Box 1)
  - "Keziah" by Eleanor H. Porter, in New England Magazine, pages 723-727, 1904 Aug; Printed (Box Box 1)
  - "Lily Ann" by Eleanor H. Porter, 11 p., with pencilled corrections and changes, TMsS (Box Box 1)
  - "Little Pard" by Eleanor H. Porter, in Smith's Magazine, pages 411-418, 1909 Jun; Printed (Box Box 1)
  - "The Man Who Fought At Home" by Eleanor H. Porter, 12 p., with pencilled corrections and changes, TMsS (Box Box 1)
  - Mary Marie by Eleanor H. Porter, 146 sheets, 1920; galleys (Box Box 2)
  - Miss Billy Married by Eleanor H. Porter, Partial Draft, Miscellaneous Pages, n.d.; AMs (Box Box 2)
  - "Money, Love and Kate" by Eleanor H. Porter, 137 pages, published as a serial in The Modern Priscilla, formerly titled "A Snowball of the Fates," with pencilled corrections and changes, ca. 1920; TMs (Box Box 2)
  - "On the Trail of the Intangible" by Eleanor H. Porter, 21 p., in Cosmopolitan, with pencilled corrections and changes, 1906; TMsS (Box Box 2)
  - "On the Trail of the Intangible" by Eleanor H. Porter, in Cosmopolitan, pages 21-30, 1906 May; Printed (Box Box 2)
  - "Polly's Day of Fun" by Eleanor H. Porter, in The Congregationalist and Christian World, pages 195-196, 1903 Aug 8; Printed (Box Box 2)
  - "Polly's Day of Fun" by Eleanor H. Porter, in The Congregationalist and Advance, page 265, 1918 Sep; Printed (Box Box 2)
  - "A Snowball of the Fates" by Eleanor H. Porter, published as a serial in 1920 in The Modern Priscilla under the title of Money, Love and Kate, ca. 1920; AMs & TMsS (Box Box 2)
  - "Strayed" by Eleanor H. Porter, 8 p., in Pearson's, with pencilled corrections and changes, 1905; 2 TMs (Box Box 2)
  - "Strayed" by Eleanor H. Porter, in Pearson's, pages 302-304, 1905; Printed (Box Box 2)
  - "Tangled" by Eleanor H. Porter, in The Blue Book Magazine, pages 1022-1046, 1908 Mar; Printed (Box Box 2)
  - "The Twins' Journey" by Eleanor H. Porter, in The Comrade, in six parts, 1911-1912; Printed (Box Box 2)
  - "A Vacation Exchange" by Eleanor H. Porter, in The Comrade, in seven chapters, 1910 Jun-Jul; Printed (Box Box 2)
  - "When Beth Came Home" by Eleanor H. Porter, in The Christian Herald, pages 217, 222, 225-226, 1914 Mar; 2 Printed (Box Box 2)
  - "When Grandma Took to Tangoing" by Eleanor H. Porter, in The Ladies Home Journal, pages 5 and 55, 1915 Aug; Printed (Box Box 2)
- Correspondence
  - Correspondence re Dawn Bookings (with Houghton Mifflin Company), 1918-1920; 33 items (Box Box 3)
    [the list of bookings includes the theater, city, and play date for Dawn; other topics in this folder include royalties, dedication of the book, and requests for Porter's autograph from the publisher]
  - Correspondence with Houghton Mifflin Company, 1917-1920; 15 items (Box Box 3)
    [includes a fan letter concerning Just David, letters from Eleanor H. Porter(carbons), R. N. Linscott, Roger L. Scaife, Ferris Greenslet, and letters about the Swedish translation of Oh, Money! Money! ]
  - Correspondence re the Just David dramatization, 1916-1924; 54 items (Box Box 3)
    [includes letters from Eleanor H. Porter(carbons), Ferris Greenslet, Roger L. Scaife, A. F. Houghton(copy), George C. Tyler, Warren E. Benson, and Grace LaSalle; and also discusses sharing the cost of legal representation over the controversy with The L.C. Page and Company involving property rights over the name "Pollyanna" (1916 Apr 21, 27, May 5, 6); and the success of Pollyanna as a play (1916 Jun 5)]
  - Correspondence re "A Minstrel of the Hills", 1910 & 1915; 14 items (Box Box 3)
    [includes letters from P. W. Hansl, editor of The Circle Magazine, Lewis E. Orcutt of The Thwing Company, Eric Schuler of The Author's League of America, and typed letter signed from Eleanor H. Porter, April 30, 1915, to Edward H. Warren, concerning the copyright to "A Minstrel of the Hills"]
  - Correspondence re Money, Love and Kate, including Eleanor H. Porter's Early Records re the manuscript, 1910-1911, 1919-1922; 34 items (Box Box 3)
    [includes letters from Thomas Newell Metcalf, Lilian D. Rice, Perriton Maxwell, fiction editor of The Modern Priscilla, Eleanor H. Porter (carbons), John Lyman Porter, and Edward H. Warren, Henry W. Newhall; and discusses changing the title of "Snowball of the Fates" (1920 Mar 8 & 10; April 21) the magazine's error in describing the story as her final work (1920 Aug 3, 6, 23, 30); and the motion picture rights to the story (1922 Oct 16,21, 23 & 31)]
  - Correspondence re "The Nickel", 1917-1920; 15 items (Box Box 3)
    [includes letters from Leon E. Dadmun, Atlas Film Corporation, and Eleanor H. Porter (carbons) about making a serial picture based on her script which was prevented by war conditions]
  - Correspondence with Publishers, 1905-1915; 72 items (Box Box 3)
    [includes letters from Frances V. Warner, John Phillips, Hollis Corbin, Lilian D. Rice, Elizabeth Jordan, Eleanor H. Porter (copy May 17, 1913), Frederick A. Stokes, Ralph T. Hale, Russell Doubleday, H. J. Jenkins, Robert Hardy, Rutger Jewett, Elizabeth Ansley, Christopher D. Morley(1915 Mar 6, May 26, Oct 1, 7; 1916 Mar 30), and Albert A. Boyden; and mentions the following short stories, "Because of Tiglath-Pileser," "The Man Who Fought At Home," "Angelus and Others," and "Lily Ann"]
  - Correspondence with Publishers, 1916-1936; 63 items (Box Box 3)
    [includes letters from Lilian D. Rice, Robert J. Shores, Verne H. Porter, Lillian Soskin, Amos R. Wells, Walter H. Baker, James E. Tower, E. V. Durling, Webb Waldron, Ethel M. Colson, Elizabeth Jordan, Eleanor H. Porter(carbons), Erich Brandeis, John T. Faris, John F. Ancona, Frank Howard Clark for Willis & Inglis Motion Picture and Theatrical Enterprises, and Edward Hemmer; also includes correspondence of John Lyman Porter with publishers and others as the executor of Eleanor Porter's estate following her death in 1920]
  - Correspondence with Short Story Magazines re copyright to Eleanor H. Porter's stories (A-L), 1907-1919; 76 items (Box Box 3)
    [letters to magazines arranged alphabetically according to the title of the magazine include The American Magazine, The Arena, The Argonaut, The Author's League of America, The Century, Christian Endeavor World, The Christian Herald, Collier's Weekly, The Comrade, The Congregationalist and Christian World, The Cosmopolitan Magazine, Countryside Magazine, The Criterion, The Designer, The Editor, The Farmer's Wife, Harper's Bazaar, Holland's Magazine, Home Progress Magazine, The Housewife, Judge, The Ladies Home Journal, Leslie's Weekly, and Lippincott's Magazine ]
  - Correspondence with Short Story Magazines re copyright to Eleanor H. Porter's stories (M-Y), 1907-1918; 63 items (Box Box 3)
    [letters to magazines include McBrides's Magazine, McCall's Magazine, The McClure Newspaper Syndicate, Metropolitan Magazine, Mother's Magazine, The Frank A. Munsey Company, Needlecraft, The New England Magazine, Pearson's Magazine, The People's Home Journal, Pictorial Review, The Pilgrim, The Pittsburgh Bulletin, Red Book Magazine, Scribner's Magazine, Short Stories, Smith's Magazine, The Springfield Republican, Street and Smith Publishers, The Suburban, Ten Story Book, Vogue, Watson's Magazine, Woman's Home Companion, The World, Young's Magazine, Youth's Companion ]
  - Correspondence re Sister Sue, 1920-1923; 24 items (Box Box 3)
    [letters include those from Paul R. Reynolds, John Lyman Porter, Sol Lesser, Frederick H. Chase, and Edward H. Warren, all discussing the motion picture rights and possible deals concerning its production]
  - Correspondence re The Story of Marco, including royalty statements from the Methodist Book Concern and a synopsis of the book, 1911-1925; 46 items (Box Box 3)
    [letters include a typed letter signed from Eleanor H. Porter, December 8, 1911, responding to a request for personal information]
- Miscellaneous Papers & Photographs
  - Legal Papers of Eleanor H. Porter, 1910-1921; 12 items (Box Box 3)
    [includes book contracts, a printed copy of her will, and blank legal forms]
  - Notes re the Publication of Eleanor H. Porter's Short Stories and Books, kept by the author, ca. 20 items (Box Box 3)
  - Photographs of Eleanor H. Porter (sepia), n.d.; 4 items
  - Photographs of Fred C. Hodgman(sepia), n.d.; 8 items
  - Photograph Albums - Vacation & Nature Scenes, n.d.; 14 items
  - Printed Material re Eleanor H. Porter, 1902-1920; 7 items (Box Box 3)